A Guide to the Laurance S. Rockefeller papers, Art Reference Files FA522
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Art Reference Card Files, 1940s - 2005; 1; 4.82 Cubic Feet 22 card file boxes
  - 834 Fifth Avenue - Photos by Room (Box 19)
    Photo file of paintings, furniture, and decorative objects, grouped roughly by room. The arrangement within and among file divisions is not reliable (many of the file dividers were missing labels), and images may be filed under more than one category or room. The photos appear to have been taken mostly around 1999, for documentation and as an inventory of furniture and artwork. (Some photos are date stamped 1994 or 1995, and there are also a few prints dated 2001.) Paintings and artwork have generally been photographed singly as individual items and not in context. In most cases duplicate prints have been removed. Box 19 is divided into the following headings: 15th Floor Living Room, 16th Floor Landing, 16th Floor Office, and 5th Floor (?).
  - 834 Fifth Avenue - General (Box 19)
    General file - paintings, sculpture, and some views. Includes images of display cabinets for china. Most photos date-stamped 1999. Approximately 22 images (duplicates have generally been removed). These photos were filed separately from the other 834 Fifth Avenue images; it is not clear if there is any particular significance to this separate grouping.
  - Meissen or Dresden Porcelain Dinnerware (Box 19)
    Photos of Meissen and/or Dresden porcelain dinnerware. Floral spray patterns on white ground. Dishes displayed on dining room table at 834 Fifth Avenue. Photos, plus negatives. (Duplicate prints have generally been removed.)
  - China Patterns (Box 19)
    Seven slides showing China patterns in LSR's collection: Dresden, Spode, Sevres, Sevres Chateau de Trianon, Worcester, Limoges, and Minton. Slides dated July 1960. Original envelope labeled "China Slides." It is not known whether there is any significance to this grouping.
  - 834 Fifth Avenue - Photos, 1999 September (Box 19)
    Furnishings and decoration, art. Two sets of color prints, 4 x 6 inches. The contact sheets and negatives for these prints are filed in Box 22, under 834 Fifth Ave and their corresponding job numbers, 916655 and 000096.
  - Echo Acre - Photos, 1999 September (Box 19)
    Interior views - paintings, artwork, furniture, rugs, and fixtures. Six sets of color prints, 4 x 6 inches. The contact sheets and negatives for these prints are filed in Box 22, under Echo Acre and their corresponding job numbers: 916625, 916646, 916647, 916649, 916654, and 916696.
    Most of the prints are date-stamped January 1994, but the contact sheets and negatives are dated September 1999.
  - Fishers Island Residence - Antique Furnishings (Box 19)
    Catalogue cards for "Furniture and Pictures at Fishers Island" (cards describe antique furniture and fixtures only, and do not include any paintings or prints). J.A. Lloyd Hyde's January 1957 appraisal of Antique Furniture in LSR's Fishers Island house was originally filed together with these cards.
  - Miscellaneous Photos - Art Work and Silver (Box 19)
    Status or location of objects unknown. 13 color prints (plus 2 duplicates).
  - Transparencies - Various Artists (Box 19)
    Color transparencies, 4 x 4.5 inches: Paul Maze (4 images); Lloyd Sexton (3 copies of one painting); Marion Weber (2 images); 1 unidentified signed painting, labeled "Argentina").
  - LSR Estate Distributions - Laura Chasin Selections and Sale, circa 2004-2005 (Box 20)
    Items received by Laura Chasin. Laura Chasin purchased $600,000 worth of items from LSR's estate and then donated them to the Public Conversations Project, a nonprofit organization she had founded in 1990. The organization then converted the items to cash, by offering them for sale to Rockefeller family members in June 2005.
    File consists of catalogue cards, polaroid prints, and some negatives. The prints or cards are frequently marked with the recipient's name or initials, or with a sticky note, but other items included in the file carry no indication of new ownership. It is difficult to know how complete these files are, or how reliably and accurately items have been sorted into and within them.
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted - LSR Estate - Open in 2029.
  - LSR Estate Distributions - Family Selections, circa 2004-2005 (Box 20)
    Restricted - LSR Estate - Open in 2029
  - LSR Estate Distributions - Family Selections, circa 2004-2005 (Box 21)
  - LSR Estate Distributions - David Rockefeller Selections, circa 2004-2005 (Box 22)
    Items David Rockefeller selected from LSR's estate, 2004 and later. File consists of catalogue cards, polaroid prints, and some negatives. The prints or cards are usually marked with David Rockefeller's initials (DR) or with a sticky note, but for several other items in the file there is no indication of ownership. It is not known how complete these files are or how reliably items have been sorted into them.
  - Contact Sheets and Negatives - General (Paintings, Artwork, Sculpture, and Porcelain), 1999 March - May (Box 22)
    Five sets of contact prints and negatives, for job numbers 699473, 699481, 706074, 706077, and 706102, March and May 1999. No effort has been made to match the images to prints elsewhere in the collection.
  - Contact Sheets and Negatives - 834 Fifth Ave - Paintings, Prints, Sculpture, 1999 May 26 (Box 22)
    Two sets of contact prints and negatives, job numbers 048281 and 048285. No effort has been made to match the images to prints elsewhere in the file.
  - Contact Sheets and Negatives - 834 Fifth Ave - Furniture, Decoration, Sculpture, Porcelain, Art, 1999 August (Box 22)
    Eight sets of contact prints and negatives, job numbers 215130, 215134, 215140, 215141, 215142, 215145, 215148, and 215150. Also includes glass, rugs, textiles. No effort has been made to match the images to prints elsewhere in the collection.
  - Contact Sheets and Negatives - 834 Fifth Ave - Paintings, 1999 February (Box 22)
    Four sets of contact prints and negatives, job numbers 269530, 269562, 269641, 269642. Photos grouped by room: Master Bedroom and Mr. R's Room; 15th Floor Living Room and Dining Room; Mr. R's Bedroom and Office; 15th Flooor Hall and Living Room. No effort has been made to match the images to prints elsewhere in the collection.
  - Contact Sheets and Negatives - 834 Fifth Avenue, 1999 September (Box 22)
    Two sets of contact prints and negatives for job numbers 916655 and 000096. See photos filed in Box 19 under the corresponding job numbers.
  - Contact Sheets and Negatives - Echo Acre, 1999 September (Box 22)
    Six sets of contact prints and negatives, job numbers 916625, 916646, 916647,916649, 916654, and 916696. See photos filed in Box 19 under the corresponding job numbers.
- Art Files, 2; 5.41 Cubic Feet 13 letter-size document boxes and 1 legal-size document box
  Arrangement
  Series 2, Art Files, is arranged in two subseries: 1) Art Collection Files - General, and 2) Art Curators' Files.
  - Art Collection Files - General, 1934-2008; 1; 1.37 Cubic Feet
    This set of general Art Collection Files consists of document files that were housed together with LSR's Art Reference Card Files. Files include inventories, appraisals, insurance valuations, catalogues and purchase records, photographs and documentation of restoration work, loan requests, and some correspondence. The records provide valuable documentation on certain aspects or portions of LSR's and MFR's art collection, but the documentation is not comprehensive, as files often are partial, are incomplete, or were inconsistently maintained.
    - Correspondence - Artwork, 1943-2003 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Correspondence concerning loans, purchases, or publication of various artworks in LSR's collection. Includes materials relating to Tseng Yuho, Milford Zornes, loan of Remington bronze (Coming through the Rye), Henry Morton, Billingsley Mansfield vases, Winslow Homer, Despiau, Erling Roberts, Monet, Dunoyer de Segonzac, John Singer Sargent (Fountain at Pocantico Hills), Ibram Lassaw, Ludovit Fulla mosaic, Larry Rivers, a Nepalese Buddha, June Harrah Lord, Resika, Ming Dynasty Buddha, bronzes for the JY Ranch.
    - Correspondence - Art Given Away, 1971-1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Chinese vases to the Cooper-Hewitt Museum; Larry Rivers, Washington Crossing the Delaware (Whitney); crystal candelabra; costumes (Museum of the City of New York); Tilly Kettle, Portrait of Mrs. John Graham (Museum of Art, Ponce).
    - Dispositions, 1997-2001 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Gifts (to Arkansas Art Center and family) and sales. Prints, Meissen china and eagle, Egyptian faience baboon.
    - Gifts to Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Gifts of paintings and artwork. Includes paintings by various African artists, Paul Maze, Paul Resika, Erling Roberts. Correspondence with Rifka Angel, 1973.
    - Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center Art Committee, 1970-2003 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Art Committee meeting reports, 1977-1990; LSR gifts, including Paul Maze paintings, Picasso tapestries; Mary French Rockefeller Chapel.
    - Fine Arts Insurance Values (2 folders), 1954-1971, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
      Correspondence concerning cataloguing, inventory revisions, and entries for new acquisitions. File also contains collection inventories, arranged by type and catalogue number. Includes valuations for paintings, sculpture, silver, furniture, china, jewelry, and Navajo rugs.
    - Fine Arts Insurance Values, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 6 A)
      Restricted - Living Rockefeller family - Restricted for Life
    - Fine Arts Insurance Coverage, 1971-1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Includes general evaluations of collections by category and location. The file also contains an undated (1950s?) list of items LSR selected from Seal Harbor, with appraised prices from a 1948 inventory.
    - Fine Arts Insurance Coverage, 1971-1981 (Box 1, Folder 8 A)
    - Restoration Work (2 folders), 1956-1969 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
      Reports and records (including photographs) of restoration work done on several paintings in LSR's and MFR's collection, mainly by Margaret M. Watherston. File also includes reports, 1958-1959, from Thomas Devine to Anice Berthier on his visits to Woodstock with Charles Uht to inventory and examine the Mansion's furniture, decoration, and paintings.
    - Repairs and Maintenance (General), 1956-1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      General file (originally labeled "Miscellaneous") concerning restoration work, furniture repair, framing, storage, etc. File also includes negatives of six St. John scenes from the Henry Morton Sketchbook (misfiled here?).
    - Loans to Exhibitions, 1968, 1972-1987 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Foujita and Winslow Homer Copies, 1994-2008 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Foujita, Mon Portrait No. 3, and Winslow Homer, Shark Fishing. The original paintings were given to Princeton University and Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, respectively. Proceeds from the sale of the Winslow Homer in 1996 were used in support of the MSKCC Wellness Center. Princeton sold the Foujita at Sotheby's Impressionist and Modern Art Sale on November 11, 1999. LSR and MFR had facsimile copies made of the two paintings in 1995 (by E. V. Thaw and Co.) and hung them in their living room at 834 Fifth Ave. File concerns both the gifts and the making of facsimile copies. Includes correspondence, photos, and LSR art cards.
    - Gifts to LSR, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      J. Wilcox painting, "Mountain Mist" (PTG-252); farmhouse scene (WC-176); piece of coral (to be displayed at Cerromar, MISC-82).
    - Artwork - Transparencies, Photographs, and Invoices, 1960-1986 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Documentation for various artworks or purchases. LSR purchase of Conrad Schwiering paintings, 1986 (with slides); photos of Portland Vase Wine Cooler (silver), purchased from James Robinson, 1981 or 1982; color transparency of pair of Meissen Woodpeckers and correspondence, 1982; color transparency of Winslow Homer, Shark Fishing; photo of plaque alongside the Akaji sculpture at Mauna Kea Beach Hotel; photograph and Henry Moore authentication, 1975, of "Rocking Chair Number One" bronze; correspondence concerning the Philanthropists of Baltimore mural at Johns Hopkins University, 1970; photos of silver punch bowl (SIL-C-14) and silver ladle (SIL-Q-19), from Museum Silver Shop (ladle purchased 1960 and shipped to Woodstock Mansion).
    - Invoices, 1966-1973 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      For purchases of paintings, prints, jewelry. Includes Zorach watercolor; paintings for Dorado Beach (Larry Rivers; possibly also Raul Russo and Raul Soldi) and for Woodstock Inn (W. W. Wilder); Navajo rugs (from John Turner); etc.
    - Woodstock, VT - Artwork, 1959-1984 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Correspondence concerning Tiffany windows and other artwork at Woodstock mansion; also concerning LSR purchases of other art related to Woodstock.
    - Furnishings for LSR Study - Theodor Muller Drawings, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      Drawings of antique furniture acquired for LSR's study in Tarrytown (Kent House).
    - Antique Furniture Appraisal - Fishers Island, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Appraisal by J.A. Lloyd Hyde. Dated January 9, 1957. See also LSR's Art Card Files, for Fishers Island Residence - Antique Furnishings, in box 19.
    - Art and Art Purchases - White House (Hawaii) and Dorado Beach Hotel, 1962-1971 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      Correspondence and inventories concerning art purchases for LSR residence (White House), Kamuela, HI, and artwork at the Dorado Beach Hotel. File also includes 1967 invoice for paintings by Viudes - possibly misfiled?
    - Wedding Book, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      Two-page listing of wedding gifts received by LSR and MFR. Partial listing of china and some furniture, plus catalogue card for silver tea caddy. Inventory includes item number and description, donor name, and where purchased.
    - Silver and China Inventories, 1946-1952, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      Inventories and packing lists for various silver and china pieces at Pocantico and New York. List of additional items LSR selected from Estate of Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, 1961.
    - Silver Collection - General, 1948-2000 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      LSR and MFR silver collection. Miscellaneous repairs, purchases, gifts, appraisals. Inventory, Tarrytown, 1948. Also includes a few invoices for framing of Audubon and other artwork.
    - Silver Collection - General, 2000-2003 (Box 2, Folder 23 A)
    - James Robinson, Inc. - LSR Estate, Silver Appraisal, 2004 November 22-24 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Antique Porcelain Company - Antique Company of New York, 1971-1986 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      Offerings and purchases of Meissen porcelain and birds; china, including Tobacco Leaf service and Sevres.
    - J. Rochelle Thomas - China and Meissen Birds, 1964-1973 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      Correspondence, invoices, and photos concerning LSR's purchases of china services and Meissen birds.
    - Chinese Porcelain at 834 Fifth Avenue (Box 3, Folder 27)
      Color 8"x10" photographs mainly of LSR's Chinese porcelain pieces and arrangements at 834 Fifth Ave. Also includes photos of two paintings and of LSR's Meissen birds and china. Photographs by Charles Uht. (Duplicates of photos in Album 86?)
    - China and Painting - Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, 1930s-1940s (Box 3, Folder 28)
      Various china dishes, services, and decorative pieces from Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, given to LSR as gifts or received from her estate. File consists of descriptive catalogue sheets and photos, often with provenance information. Also includes one sheet for Rousseau painting, "The Palette."
    - Japanese and Indian Purchases, 1962-1964 (Box 3, Folder 29)
      Mughal paintings, figurines (Avalikiteshwar, Lama Buddha), textiles, Japanese lacquer ware; Japanese paintings and prints; porcelain and pottery; bronze pieces and Buddha.
    - Christie's and Sotheby's Bids (LSR), 1998 (Box 3, Folder 30)
      Indian and Southeast Asian Art auctions. LSR bid successfully on a bronze Buddha Shakyamuni from Christie's.
    - Art Catalogues and Sales, 1971-1984 (Box 3, Folder 31)
      Harry Bertoia brochures; Paul Resika exhibit brochures, slide, and letter to MFR, 1979; Georgette Rutherford show, 1971; Shirley Russell paintings; letter from NAR to LSR, concerning Meissen parrots and bitterns from the Dunlap collection, offered by Sotheby Parke Bernet, December 1975.
    - Erling Roberts, Virgin Islands Paintings (Photographs), circa 1972 (Box 3, Folder 32)
      Photographs of six scenic paintings, mainly of views from Caneel Bay. Includes PTG-226, PTG-227, PTG-253, and possibly PTG-254. Two paintings given to Memorial Sloan Kettering in 1973. See Gifts to MSK folder.
    - Stuart and Turner Ltd. - Photographs (4 Folders), 1940s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 33-36)
      Photograph file of fine English furniture and other items, presumably offered for sale by Stuart and Turner, Ltd., of London. Photos include detailed descriptions of the items. Some photos include LSR catalogue numbers or other information. File includes one invoice for a purchase LSR made in 1963. File also includes some photos of glass, silver, or china pieces.
    - Fine Art and Sculpture - General (Box 3, Folder 37)
      Color slides of paintings and sculpture from LSR's collection - 15 objects (32 slides, including duplicate images). Slides were housed in slide boxes at end of the Art Card Files. One box was labeled "L.A. Rocke, 4/87."
    - Paintings - 834 Fifth Ave - Negative Strips, 7 sets of 35mm color negatives, for the most part cut into 6-inch strips. (Box 3, Folder 38)
      Seven sets of negatives: paintings; Mr. R's Office; Mrs. R's Room and Lucy's Room; 14th-Floor Hall; "Random" (paintings); Gallery (2 sets).
    - Silver Collection - Negative Strips, 35mm black and white negatives, cut for the most part into 6-inch strips. (Box 3, Folder 39)
      10 sets of negative strips. Images of silver pieces and a few pieces of jewelry. No other identification or description.
    - Lucy Truman Aldrich Bequest, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 40)
      Lists of items chosen by LSR and MFR from the estate of Lucy Truman Aldrich.
    - Martha Baird Rockefeller Estate Distribution, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 41)
      Exhibit L, Articles Distributed to Laurance S. Rockefeller.
    - LSR Estate and MFR (Mary French Rockefeller) Estate - General, 1998, 2005, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 42)
      Disposition of low-value items; Staff gifts; donation of MFR gowns and clothing to the Museum of the City of New York.
    - LSR Estate - General, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 42 A)
    - LSR Estate - Items Given Away, 2004-2005 (Box 4, Folder 43)
      Steuben sailboat to David Rockefeller; book to Carolyn Sheffield.
    - LSR Estate - Selection Procedures and General Disposition, 2004-2005 (Box 4, Folder 44)
      Procedures for family selections, miscellaneous and low-value items, archival materials, wine cellar inventory, apartment repairs. Donation of Demuth's "Red Gladioli" to the Whitney Museum.
    - LSR Estate - Selection Procedures and General Disposition, 2004-2005 (Box 4, Folder 44 A)
    - History of LSR Art Card File, 2008 (Box 4, Folder 45)
      Memo from Ruth Haupert, LSR's assistant, describing the creation and organization of LSR's art reference card catalogue. This memo was created around December 2008, when the catalogue file was transferred to the Rockefeller Archive Center.
    - Separated Materials and Redacted Originals from Art Reference Card Files (Box 4, Folder 46)
      File contains restricted materials separated from the Art Reference Card Files and the originals of redacted cards and items. Separation sheets are filed in place in the card file, with cross-reference information to this file.
      When items are redacted, the redacted copies replace the originals in the card file. The originals of redacted items are removed and interfiled in this folder along with the other separated material, but no separation sheet is used. The original file location is noted for each of these redacted originals.
      In some cases, redacted items have not been marked up, as photocopying the image without its border effectively obscures the restricted information.
  - Art Curators' Files, 1935-2006; 2
    The Art Curators' Files consist of art records gathered and maintained by LSR's and MFR's curators, Kendall P. Lutkins and Leith R. Talamo. The files date mainly from the 1970s to the early 2000s, though the series also includes several records from the 1950s or earlier. While these records were filed separately from the Art Collection Files in Series 2.1, they overlap in the nature of the documents and their subjects and contents. The subseries includes inventories, appraisals, and insurance valuations; purchase and sale records; records of gifts and donations; auction catalogues; files on individual artists; and records on LSR's porcelain, silver, Native American, and Asian art collecting.
    - Art Collection and Appraisals - General, 1954-1955, 1973-1981, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 47)
      General file, mainly concerning purchases and gifts. Includes donation of books, painting, and costumes to Marsh Billings Rockefeller National Historical Park, 2004; purchase of Matisse drawing of Ida Chagall, 1974; purchase of Von Kaulbach portrait of Edith Rockefeller McCormick, 1976; Demuth, Red Gladiola watercolor; Dwight Shepler paintings; list of LSR paintings loaned to Dorado Beach Hotel, 1975. Also includes undated list of Insured Art Work, with estimated values, circa 1950s?
    - List of Appraisals, 1981-1995 (Box 4, Folder 48)
      Summary details, locations, and dates for various appraisals of LSR's and MFR's collections.
    - Fine Arts Reports, 1974-1977 (Box 4, Folder 49)
      Quarterly or semi-annual reports on art acquisitions or deaccessions.
    - Fine Arts Insurance Values, 1978-1989 (Box 4, Folder 50)
      File mainly consists of quarterly reports stating, for the purposes of insurance coverage, the change in value of LSR's art collection.
    - Art Appraisals - General, 1959-1997 (Box 4, Folder 51)
      Appraisal of fine art and furniture (at 834 Fifth Ave and Kent House) belonging to the Estate of Mary French Rockefeller, 1997; Vlaminck Landscape, 1972; Art at Kykuit, 1972; Downtown Gallery valuation of art pieces, 1959; claim for stolen antique chairs, 1992.
    - Art Appraisals - General, 1979-1989, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 52)
      Scheduling and arrangements for appraisals of LSR's fine art collections in his various residences, 1979. Appraisals by Graham Gallery and E. V. Thaw, 1979, 1985, and 1988. Includes some purchases and invoices: sets of Sevres coffee "cans" and saucers (with photos), 1980; Navajo and Germantown rugs, 1989. Appraisal of Sioux beaded vest, 1983. Also includes Carl C. Dauterman request to study porcelains decorated with birds in LSR's collection, 1979.
    - James Graham and Sons - Insurance Appraisals, 1979, 1988, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 53)
      Appraisals of art at Woodstock, 834 Fifth Avenue, JY Ranch, and Kent House.
    - E.V. Thaw and Company, 1979-1988, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 54)
      Fine Art appraisals, 1979, 1983, 1986, 1988; consignment for sale on behalf of LSR Fund of paintings by Braque and Matisse, 1995.
    - Sotheby's and Christie's Appraisals, 1983, 1993-1994, 1999-2002 (Box 4, Folder 55)